Someone once said that politics is, of course, "showbiz for ugly people."
أحدهم مرة قال أن "السياسة" هي بالطبع "شوبيز للأشخاص القبيحين"
So, on that basis, I feel like I've really arrived.
ومن هذا المنطلق, أشعر بأنني وصلت بالفعل
The other thing to think of is what an honor it is, as a politician,
الشئ الاخر لتفكر فيه هو الشرف الذي تحظى به كسياسي
to give a TED talk, particularly here in the U.K.,
لإلقاء محاضرة تيد وخصوصا هنا في المملكة المتحدة
where the reputation of politics, with the expenses scandal, has sunk so low.
حيث سمعة السياسة ، مع فضيحة النفقات ، قد غرقت بانخفاض جدا
There was even a story recently that scientists had thought about
وكانت هناك قصة في الآونة الأخيرة أن العلماء قد فكروا
actually replacing rats in their experiments with politicians.
في الواقع باستبدال الفئران في تجاربهم محل السياسيين
And someone asked,"Why?"
وسأل أحدهم "لماذا؟"
and they said, "Well, there's no shortage of politicians,
وقالوا : "حسنا ، ليس هناك نقص في السياسيين
no one really minds what happens to them
لا أحد يكترث بما يحصل لهم
and, after all, there are some things that rats just won't do."
وفوق كل ذلك ، هناك بعض الأشياء التي لن تفعلها الفئران ".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, I know you all love data, so I'm starting with a data-rich slide.
الآن ، أنا أعلم أنكم تحبون البيانات ، لذلك سأبدأ بشريحة غنية بالبيانات
This, I think, is the most important fact to bear in mind
هذا ، في اعتقادي ، هي أهم حقيقة يجب أن توضع في الإعتبار
in British politics or American politics,
في السياسة البريطانية أو السياسة الأميركية
and that is: We have run out of money.
وهي, لقد نفدت نقودنا
We have vast budget deficits.
لدينا عجز واسع في الميزانية
This is my global public debt clock,
هذه هي ساعة الديون العامة العالمية الخاصة بي
and, as you can see, it's 32 trillion and counting.
كما ترون فهو ٣٢ ترليون وبازدياد
And I think what this leads to
وأعتقد أن ما هذا يؤدي إلى
is a very simple recognition,
هو اعتراف بسيط جدا
that there's one question in politics at the moment above all other,
ان هناك سؤال واحد في السياسة في هذه اللحظة قبل كل شيء آخر
and it's this one: How do we make things better without spending more money?
وهذا هو : كيف لنا أن نجعل الأمور أفضل من دون إنفاق المزيد من المال؟
Because there isn't going to be a lot of money to improve public services,
لأنه لن يكون هناك الكثير من الاموال لتحسين الخدمات العامة
or to improve government, or to improve so many of the things
أو لتحسين الحكومة ، أو لتحسين الكثير من الاشياء
that politicians talk about.
التي يتحدث عنها السياسيين
So what follows from that is that if you think it's all about money --
لذلك ما يلي من هذا هو أنه إذا كنت تعتقد أن الأمر كله يتعلق بالمال
you can only measure success in public services
يمكنك فقط قياس مدى النجاح في مجال الخدمات العامة
in health care and education and policing by spending more money,
في الرعاية الصحية والتعليم والشرطة من خلال انفاق المزيد من المال
you can only measure progress by spending money --
ويمكنك فقط قياس التقدم عن طريق انفاق المال
you're going to have a pretty miserable time.
سوف تقضي وقتا تعيسا جدا.
But if you think a whole lot of other things matter that lead up to well being --
لكن إذا كنت تعتقد بأن أمور اخرى بأسرها مهمة, هذا سيؤدي الى الرفاء
things like your family relationships, friendship, community, values --
أشياء مثل علاقاتك الأسرية ، الصداقة ، والمجتمع ، والقيم ،
then, actually, this is an incredibly exciting time to be in politics.
ثم ، في الواقع ، هذا هو الوقت الأكثر إثارة لتكون في السياسة
And the really simple argument I want to make tonight,
وحجة بسيطة حقا أريد أن أقولها هذه الليلة ،
the really straightforward argument is this:
الحجة الواضحة فعلا هي أنه
That if we combine the right political philosophy, the right political thinking,
إذا جمعنا الفلسفلة السياسية الصحيحة والتفكير السياسي الصحيح
with the incredible information revolution that has taken place,
مع ثورة المعلومات الهائلة التي حدثت ،
and that all of you know so much more about than I do,
والتي جميعكم تعرفون عنها أكثر بكثير عما أعلم
I think there's an incredible opportunity to actually remake politics,
اعتقد ان هناك فرصة لا تصدق فعلا لاعادة صياغة السياسة
remake government, remake public services,
إعادة تشكيل الحكومة ، وإعادة تشكيل الخدمات العامة
and achieve what's up on that slide, which is a big increase in our well-being.
وتحقيق ما هو موجود في الشريحة , وهو ما يمثل زيادة كبيرة في رفاهيتنا.
That's the argument I want to make tonight.
هذه الحجة التي أريد أن أقولها الليلة
So, starting with the political philosophy.
لذلك ، بدءا من الفلسفة السياسية.
Now I'm not saying for a minute that British Conservatives have all the answers.
الآن لست أقول للحظة واحدة أن حزب المحافظين البريطاني لديه جميع الإجابات.
Of course we don't.
بطبيعة الحال ، فلسنا كذلك
But there are two things at heart that I think drive a conservative philosophy
ولكن هناك شيئين في الصميم ، وأعتقد بأنهما يحركان الفلسفلة المحافظة
that are really relevant to this whole debate.
التي هي في الحقيقة ذات صلة في هذا النقاش كله.
The first is this: We believe that if you give people
الأول هو هذا ، فإننا نعتقد أنه إذا توفر للناس
more power and control over their lives,
مزيد من السلطة والسيطرة على حياتهم ،
if you give people more choice,
إذا أعطيت الناس خيارات اكثر
if you put them in the driving seat,
إذا وضعتهم في مقعد القيادة ،
then actually, you can create a stronger and better society.
ففي الواقع ، يمكنك خلق مجتمع أفضل وأقوى
And if you marry this fact with the incredible abundance
وإذا زاوجت هذه الحقيقة مع وفرة عظيمة
of information that we have in our world today,
من المعلومات التي لدينا في عالمنا اليوم ،
I think you can completely, as I've said,
اعتقد انكم تستطيعون تماما ، كما قلت ،
remake politics, remake government, remake your public services.
اعادة صياغة السياسة ، إعادة صياغة الحكومة ، وإعادة صياغة خدماتكم العامة
The second thing we believe is we believe in going with the grain of human nature.
الشيء الثاني في اعتقادنا ، هو أننا نعتقد بالرجوع للأصل في الطبيعة البشرية
Politics and politicians will only succeed
السياسة والسياسيون سينجحون فقط
if they actually try and treat with people as they are,
أذا كانو فعلا يحاولون أن يعالجوا الأشخاص كما هم
rather than as they would like them to be.
وليس كما يودون أن يكونوا عليه
Now, if you combine this very simple, very conservative thought --
الآن ، إذا قمت بدمج هذه الفكرة البسيطة جدا ، ومتحفظة للغاية -
go with the grain of human nature --
اذهب بأصل الطبيعة البشرية
with all the advances in behavioral economics,
مع كل هذا التقدم في الاقتصاد السلوكي
some of which we were just hearing about,
بعض مما سمعنا عنه للتو
again, I think we can achieve a real increase in well-being,
مرة أخرى ، أعتقد أنه يمكننا تحقيق زيادة حقيقية في مستوى الرفاهية
in happiness, in a stronger society
في السعادة ، في مجتمع أقوى
without necessarily having to spend a whole lot more money.
دون اللجوء بالضرورة الى انفاق الكثير من المال.
Now, why do I think now is the moment to make this argument?
الآن ، لماذا اعتقد ان هذا هو الوقت المناسب للإدلاء بهذه الحجة؟
Well, I'm afraid you're going to suffer a short, condensed history lesson
حسنا, اخشى بأنكم ستعانون من حصة تاريخ قصيرة ومكثفة
about what I would say are the three passages of history:
عن ما أود أن أقوله في هذه المقاطع الثلاثة من التاريخ
the pre-bureaucratic age, the bureaucratic age
عصر ما قبل البيروقراطية ، عصر البيروقراطية
and what we now live in, which I think is a post-bureaucratic age.
وما نعيشه الان ، وهو ما أعتقد أنه في مرحلة ما بعد عصر البيروقراطية.
A simpler way of thinking of it
وهناك طريقة أبسط للتفكير فيه
is that we have gone from a world of local control,
هو أن نكون قد انتقلنا من عالم من السيطرة المحلية
then we went to a world of central control,
ثم ذهبنا إلى عالم من السيطرة المركزية
and now we're in a world of people control.
ونحن الآن في عالم من سيطرة الشعب.
Local power, central power, now, people power.
السلطة المحلية والسلطة المركزية ، والآن ، وسلطة الشعب
Now, here is King Cnut, king a thousand years ago.
الآن ، ها هو الملك كنوت، ملك الف سنة مضت.
Thought he could turn back the waves; couldn't turn back the waves.
اعتقد أنه كان يستطيع العودة الى الوراء. لا يمكن العودة الى الوراء.
Couldn't actually turn back very much,
في الواقع لم يتمكن من العودة كثيرا
because if you were king a thousand years ago,
لانك إذا كنت ملكا الف سنة مضت
while it still took hours and hours and weeks and weeks to traverse your own country,
في حين انك لا تزال تستغرق ساعات وساعات واسابيع واسابيع لاجتياز بلدك ،
there wasn't much you were in charge of.
لم يكن الكثير الذي كنت مسؤولا عنها.
You weren't in charge of policing, justice, education, health, welfare.
أنك لم تكن مسؤولا عن الشرطة والعدل والتعليم والصحة والرعاية الاجتماعية.
You could just about go to war and that was about it.
يمكنك فقط الذهاب للحرب وهذا كان كل الموضوع
This was the pre-bureaucratic age,
هذا هو عصر ما قبل البيروقراطية ،
an age in which everything had to be local.
عصر حيث كل شيء كان لا بد أن يكون محلي
You had to have local control because there was no nationally-available information
هل كان لديها سيطرة المحلية بسبب عدم وجود المعلومات المتاحة على الصعيد الوطني
because travel was so restricted.
لأن السفر كان مقيد جدا
So this was the pre-bureaucratic age.
لذلك كان هذا عصر ما قبل البيروقراطية.
Next part of the cold history lesson,
الجزء التالي من درس التاريخ المعقد
the lovely picture of the British Industrial Revolution.
الصورة الجميلة من الثورة الصناعية البريطانية.
Suddenly, all sorts of transport, travel information were possible,
فجأة ، جميع أنواع النقل والسفر ومعلومات باتت ممكنة
and this gave birth to, what I like to call, the bureaucratic age.
وهذا أنجب ما يحلو لي أن أسميه ، عصر البيروقراطية.
And hopefully this slide is going to morph beautifully. There we are.
ونأمل أن هذه الشريحة ستتطور جميلا. ها هي
Suddenly, you have the big, strong, central state.
فجأة لديك القوى الكبيرة, القوية المركزية
It was able -- but only it was able -- to organize
كانت قادرة, فقط قادرة على تنطيم
health care, education, policing, justice.
الرعاية الصحية والتعليم والشرطة والعدالة.
And it was a world of, as I say, not local power, but now central power.
وكان عالم ، كما أقول ، لا السلطة المحلية ، ولكن الآن السلطة المركزية.
It had sucked all that power up from the localities.
انه امتص كل الطاقة التي تصل من المحليات.
It was able to do that itself.
استطاعت أن تفعل ذلك لوحدها
The next great stage, which all of you are so familiar with:
المرحلة المقبلة العظيمة ، التي جميعكم على دراية بها
the massive information revolution.
ثورة المعلومات الهائلة.
Just consider this one fact:
فقط انظر الى هذه الحقيقة الوحيدة
One hundred years ago, sending these 10 words cost 50 dollars.
قبل 100 سنة ، إرسال هذه ال 10 كلمات يكلف 50 دولارا.
Right now, here we are linked up to Long Beach and everywhere else,
حاليا, ها نحن نرتبط مع لونغ بيتش وكل مكان اخر
and all these secret locations for a fraction of that cost,
وجميع هذه المواقع السرية لجزء من تلك التكاليف ،
and we can send and receive huge quantities of information
ويمكننا إرسال واستقبال كميات ضخمة من المعلومات
without it costing anything.
دون أن يكلف أي شيء.
So we're now living in a post-bureaucratic age,
لذلك نحن نعيش الآن في عصر ما بعد البيروقراطية ،
where genuine people power is possible.
حيث سلطة الشعب الحقيقية ممكنة
Now, what does this mean for our politics,
الآن ، ماذا يعني هذا بالنسبة سياساتنا ،
for our public services, for our government?
لخدماتنا العامة ، ولحكومتنا؟
Well I can't, in the time I've got, give huge numbers of examples,
حسنا, لا أستطيع في الوقت المحدد لي أن أعطي كما هائلا من الأمثلة
but let me just give a few of the ways that life can change.
ولكن اسمحوا لي مجرد اعطاء عدد قليل من السبل التي من شأنها أن تغير الحياة.
And this is so obvious, in a way, because
وهذا واضح للغاية ، بطريقة ما ، لأن
you think about how all of you have changed
تفكرون كيف أن جميعكم قد تغير
the way we shop, the way we travel, the way that business is done.
طريقتنا في التسوق ، وطريقتنا في السفر ، والطريقة التي تتم فيها أعمالنا.
That is already happened; the information and Internet revolution
هذا هو ما حدث بالفعل ، ثورة المعلومات والانترنت
has actually gone all the way through our societies in so many different ways,
دخلت في مجتمعاتنا بطرق كثيرة مختلفة
but it hasn't, in every way, yet touched our government.
لكنها لم تطرق لحكوماتنا بأي من الطرق
So, how could this happen?
لذلك ، كيف يمكن أن يحدث هذا؟
Well, I think there are three chief ways that it should make an enormous difference:
حسنا ، أعتقد أن هناك ثلاث طرق رئيسية ينبغي أن تقدم الفارق الهائل ،
in transparency, in greater choice and in accountability,
في الشفافية ، والمزيد من الخيارات ، والمساءلة ،
in giving us that genuine people power.
في إعطائنا قوة الشعب الحقيقية تلك
If we take transparency, here is one of my favorite websites,
إذا ما أخذنا في الشفافية ، وهذا هو واحد من مواقع الشبكة المفضلة لدي،
the Missouri Accountability Portal.
بوابة سورري للمساءلة
In the old days, only the government could hold the information,
في الأيام الخوالي, فقط الحكومة تستطيع أن تتستر على المعلومات
and only a few elected people could try and grab that information
والقليل من الأشخاص المنتخبين فقط يستطيعون أن يحاولوا أن يحصلوا على تلك المعلومات
and question it and challenge it.
ومساءلتها وتحديها
Now here, on one website, one state in America,
الآن هنا ، في موقع واحد ، ولاية واحدة في أميركا
every single dollar spent by that government
كل دولار أنفق من قبل الحكومة
is searchable, is analyzable, is checkable.
هو قابل للبحث ، هو قابل للتحليل ، هو قابل للفحص
Think of the huge change that means:
فكروا في التغيير الهائل الذي يعني
Any business that wants to bid for a government contract
أي شركة تود أن تحصل على عقد مع الحكومة
can see what currently is being spent.
يمكنها أن ترى ما يتم إنفاقه
Anyone thinking, "I could do that service better, I could deliver it cheaper,"
أي شخص يفكر, أستطيع أن أقوم بهذه الخدمة أفضل, أو أستطيع أن أسلمه بأرخص
it's all available there.
إنه كله متاح هنا
We have only, in government and in politics,
لدينا فقط ، في الحكومة وفي السياسة
started to scratch the surface of what people are doing in the commercial world
بدأنا بنقش ما يقوم به الناس في عالمهم التجاري
with the information revolution.
مع ثورة المعلومات
So, complete transparency will make a huge difference.
لذلك ،الشفافية الكاملة ستشكل فارقا ضخما.
In this country, if we win the election,
في هذا البلد ، إذا فزنا في الانتخابات ،
we are going to make all government spending over 25,000 pounds
سوف نجعل كل الإنفاق الحكومي الذي فوق ٢٥٠٠٠ جنيه
transparent and available online, searchable for anyone to see.
شفافاً ومتاحاً على شبكة الإنترنت ، للبحث عنه من قبل أي شخص يريد أن يرى.
We're going to make every contract -- we're announcing this today --
سوف نجعل كل العقود, ونعلن هذا اليوم
available on the Internet so anyone can see
متاحاً على الإنترنت, لكي يراها أي شخص
what the terms are, what the conditions are,
ما هي الشروط, وما هي الظروف
driving huge value for money,
سوف تستمد قيمة كبيرة للمال
but also huge increases, I believe, in well-being as well.
ولكن باعتقادي كذلك, زيادة هائلة في الرفاهية كذلك
Choice. Now you all shop online, compare online, do everything online,
الاختيار. الآن لكم جميعا التسوق عبر الانترنت ، المقارنة على الانترنت ، وتفعل كل شيء عبر الانترنت ،
and yet this revolution has hardly touched the surface
وبعد, فهذه الثورة لا تكاد تلمس سطح
of public services like education, or health care or policing,
الخدمات العامة مثل التعليم ، أو الرعاية الصحية ، أو الشرطة
and you're going to see this change massively.
وسترون هذا يتغير بسرعة
We should be making this change
ينبغي لنا أن إجراء هذا التغيير
with the information revolution in our country,
مع ثورة المعلومات في بلدن
with searchable health sites, so you can see what operations work out properly,
مع مواقع البحث الصحية, لكي يتسنى لك مشاهدة ما هي العمليات التي تقام على الوجه الصحيح
what records doctors have, the cleanliness of hospitals,
ما هي السجلات لدى الأطباء, نظافة المستشفيات
who does best at infection control --
من الأفضل في مكافحة العدوى
all of the information that would once be locked in the Department of Health
كل المعلومات التي كانت من شأنها مؤمن عليها في دائرة الصحة
is now available for all of us to see.
متوفرة الان للجميع لكي يروها
And the third of these big changes: accountability.
وثالث هذه التغيرات الكبيرة ، هي المساءلة
This, I think, is a huge change.
هذا ، في اعتقادي ، هو تغيير هائل.
It is a crime map. This is a crime map from Chicago.
انها خريطة جريمة. هذه هي خريطة جريمة من شيكاغو.
So, instead of having a situation where only the police have the information
لذلك بدلا من أن يكون هناك موقف تكون المعلومات لدى الشرطة فقط
about which crimes are committed where,
عن أي من الجرائم التي تم ارتكابها وفي أي مكان
and we have to employ people in government
علينا أن نوظف أشخاص في الحكومة
to try and hold the police to account,
في محاولة لجعل الشرطة مسؤولة
suddenly, we've got this vast opportunity for people power,
فجأة لدينا هذه الفرصة الواسعة لسلطة الشعب
where we, as citizens, can see what crimes are being committed --
حيث نستطيع ، نحن المواطنين ، ونرى ما هي الجرائم التي يجري ارتكابها ،
where, when and by whom --
أين ومتى وعلى يد من
and we can hold the police to account.
ويمكننا أن نحمل الشرطة المسؤولية
And you can see this looks a bit like a chef's hat,
ويمكنكم أن تروا أن هذا ، يشبه قليلا قبعة قائد ،
but actually that's an assault, the one in blue.
ولكن في الواقع أن هذا اعتداء ، تلك التي بالأزرق
You can see what crime is committed where,
يمكنك أن ترى ما هي الجريمة التي ارتكبت وأين
and you have the opportunity to hold your police force to account.
ولديكم الفرصة لتحميل القوة الشرطية المسؤولية
So those three ways -- transparency, accountability and choice --
فهذه الطرق الثلاث ، والشفافية ، والمساءلة ، والاختيار ،
will make a huge difference.
ستحدث فارقا ضخما
Now I also said the other principle
الان لقد تكلمت عن المبدأ الاخر
that I think we should work on is understanding of people,
أنه باعتقادي ما يجب العمل عليه هو فهم الناس
is recognizing that going with the grain of human nature
والإعتراف بأن الذهاب للطبيعة البشرية
you can achieve so much more.
يمكنك تحقيق أكثر من ذلك بكثير.
Now, we're got a huge revolution in understanding
الآن ، حصلنا على ثورة هائلة في فهم
of why people behave in the way that they do,
لماذا يتصرف الناس في الطريقة التي يتصرفون بها
and a great opportunity to put that knowledge and information to greater use.
وفرصة كبيرة لوضع هذه المعلومات والمعرفة لاستخدام أكثر
We're working with some of these people.
نحن نعمل مع بعض من هؤلاء الناس.
We're being advised by some of these people, as was said,
لقد تم نصحنا من قبل بعض الأشخاص كما قيل
to try and bring all the experience to book.
في محاولة لجمع كل التجارب في كتاب.
Let me just give you one example that I think is incredibly simple, and I love.
اسمحوا لي فقط أن أعطيك مثالا واحدا أعتقد أنه بسيط بشكل لا يصدق ، وأنا أحبه
We want to get people to be more energy efficient.
نحن نريد الأشخاص أن يكونوا أكثر كفاءة في استخدام الطاقة
Why? It cuts fuel poverty, it cuts their bills,
لماذا؟ وتخفيض حدة الفقر من الوقود ، وذلك بخفض فواتيرهم ،
and it cuts carbon emissions at the same time.
وخفض انبعاثات الكربون في نفس الوقت.
How do you do it?
كيف يمكنك أن تفعل ذلك؟
Well, we've had government information campaigns over the years
حسنا, لقد كان لدينا الحملات الإعلانية الحكومية على مر السنين
when they tell you to switch off the lights when you leave the home.
التي كانت تخبركم لماذا يخبروكم بإطفاء الإضاءة عند مغادرة المنزل
We even had -- one government minister once told us to
حتى أننا كان لدينا, مرة أخبرنا وزير حكومي مرة بأنه يجب
brush our teeth in the dark.
أن أسوّك أسناني في الظلام
I don't think they lasted very long.
لا أعتقد بأنهم استمروا لفترة طويلة جدا
Look at what this does. This is a simple piece of behavioral economics.
انظر الى ماذا يفعل هذا. هذا هو جزء بسيط من الاقتصاد السلوكي
The best way to get someone to cut their electricity bill
أفضل طريقة لتقليل فاتورة الكهرباء لشخص
is to show them their own spending,
هي أن تريهم نفقاتهم
to show them what their neighbors are spending,
و أن تريهم ما ينفقه جيرانهم
and then show what an energy conscious neighbor is spending.
ومن ثم أن تريهم ما ينفقه الجار الواعي من الطاقة
That sort of behavioral economics
هذا النوع من الاقتصاد السلوكي
can transform people's behavior
يمكنه تحويل سلوك الإنسان
in a way that all the bullying and all the information
بطريقة أن كل البلطجة وجميع المعلومات
and all the badgering from a government cannot possibly achieve.
وكل تلك المضايقات من الحكومة لا يمكن أن تحققه
Other examples are recycling.
ومن الأمثلة الأخرى ، إعادة التدوير.
We all know we need to recycle more.
نعلم جميعا أننا بحاجة إلى زيادة في إعادة التدوير
How do we make it happen?
كيف يمكننا تحقيق ذلك؟
All the proof from America is that actually, if you pay people to recycle,
كل الادلة من اميركا هو ، في الواقع ، اذا كنت تدفع الناس لإعادة تدوير ،
if you give them a carrot rather than a stick,
إذا أعطيت لهم الجزرة وليس العصا
you can transform their behavior.
يمكنك تغيير سلوكهم.
So what does all this add up to?
فماذا يضيف كل هذا الى الأمر؟
Here are my two favorite U.S. speeches of the last 50 years.
هنا الخطابان الإمريكيان المفضلان لدي على مر ال ٥٠ سنة
Obviously, here we have JFK with that incredibly simple
هنا لدينا جون كينيدي مع تلك البساطة المذهلة
and powerful formulation,
وصياغة قوية ،
"Ask not what your country can do for you; ask what you can do for your country,"
"لا تسأل عما يمكن أن يفعله بلدك لك ؛ اسأل ما يمكنك القيام به لبلدكم ،"
an incredibly noble sentiment.
شعور نبيل لا يصدق
But when he made that speech, what could you do
ولكن عندما القى هذا الخطاب ، ماذا يمكن أن تفعله
to build the stronger, better society?
لبناء الدعم الأقوى للمجتمع؟
You could fight for your country, you could die for your country,
يمكنك أن تكافح من أجل بلدك, يمكنك أن تموت فداء لبلدك
you could serve in your country's civil service,
يمكنك أن تعمل في الخدمة المدنية لبلدك
but you didn't really have the information and the knowledge
ولكنك في الواقع لم تكن لديك المعلومات والمعرفة
and the ability to help build the stronger society in the way that you do now.
والقدرة على المساعدة في بناء مجتمع أقوى في الطريقة التي يمكنك القيام به الآن.
And I think an even more wonderful speech,
وأعتقد أن خطاب أكثر روعة
which I'm going to read a big chunk of,
الذي سأقرأ جزءا كبيرا منه
which sums up what I said at the beginning
التي يلخص ما قلته في البداية
about believing there is more to life than money,
عن الاعتقاد هناك ما هو أكثر من المال في الحياة
and more that we should try and measure than money.
والكثير مما يجب علينا تجربته وتدبيره من المال
And it is Robert Kennedy's beautiful description
وهو وصف روبرت كينيدي الجميل
of why gross national product captures so little:
عن لماذا الناتج الإجمالي القومي يلتقط القليل
It "does not allow for the health of our children,
انه "لا يسمح للصحة في أطفالنا ،
the quality of their education, or the joy of their play.
الجودة في تعليمهم أو المتعة في لعبهم
It does not include the beauty of our poetry or the strength of our marriages,
لا يجمل أشعارنا أو يقوي علاقاتنا الزوجية
the intelligence of our public debate.
الذكاء في نقاشاتنا العامة
It measures neither our wit nor our courage,
إنه لا يقيس لا طرافتنا ولا شجاعتنا
neither our wisdom nor our learning,
لا حكمتنا ولا تعليمنا
neither our compassion nor our devotion to our country.
لا تعاطفنا ولا إخلاصنا لبلدنا.
It measures everything, in short,
يقيس كل شئ, باختصار
except that which makes life worthwhile."
الا ذلك الذي يجعل الحياة قيمة
Again, a sentiment that was so noble and beautifully put 40 years ago,
مرة اخرى, مشاعر جدا نبيلة وجميلة وضعت قبل ٤٠ سنة مضت
and a beautiful dream 40 years ago,
وحلم جميل منذ ٤٠ سنة
but now with the huge advances in information technology,
ولكن الآن مع التقدم الهائل في تكنولوجيا المعلومات ،
with the massive changes in behavioral economics,
مع تغيرات هائلة في الاقتصاد السلوكي ،
with all that we know about how you advance well-being,
مع كل ما نعرفه عن الكيفية التي من شأنها تعزيز الرفاهية
that if we combine those insights
إذا كان لنا أن الجمع بين هذه الأفكار
of giving power to people, and using information to make that possible,
من إعطاء السلطة للشعب ، واستخدام المعلومات لجعل ذلك ممكنا ،
and using the insight of going with the grain of human nature,
واستخدام البصيرة للذهاب مع الطبيعة البشرية
while at the same time, understanding why people behave in the way they do,
بينما في نفس الوقت ، فهم لماذا يتصرف الناس بالطريقة التي يتصرفون بها ،
it is a dream more easy to realize today
فهو حلم أكثر من السهل ان ندركه اليوم
than it was when it was made in that beautiful speech 40 years ago.
مما كان عليه في تلك الكلمة الجميلة منذ ٤٠ سنة مضت
Thank you.
شكرا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)